ILGWU. Local 10. Managers' correspondence 5780/011
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ILGWU. Local 10. Managers' correspondence
1942-1969
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Nagler, Isidore, 1895-
Falikman, Moe
Local 10
International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union
5780/011
8.5 cubic feet
8.5 linear ft.
Correspondence, reports, photographs.
This collection contains the correspondence of two of Local 10 managers, Isidore Nagler and Moe Falikman.
5457237
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, May 20, 2014
EAD encoding:
Kathryn Dowgiewicz, May 20, 2014
Biographical / Historical
Founded in 1900 by local union delegates representing about 2,000 members in cities in the northeastern United States, the ILGWU grew in geographical scope, membership size, political influence to become one of the most powerful forces in American organized labor by mid-century. Representing workers in the women's garment industry, the ILGWU worked to improve working and living conditions of its members through collective bargaining agreements, training programs, health care facilities, cooperative housing, educational opportunities, and other efforts. In 1995, the ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union (ACTWU) to form the Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE).
Biographical / Historical
Isidore Nagler (1895-1959) came to the United States from Austria-Hungary in 1909 and joined Local 10 of the ILGWU in 1911. He held various positions within the ILGWU, including business agent of Local 10, manager of the New York Cloak Joint Board, International vice president, and manager of the New York Joint Board of the Cloak, Shirt, Skirt and Reefer Makers' Union. He was also involved in the work of the New York State Federation of Labor, American Federation of Labor, American Labor Party, Liberal Party, and the Jewish Labor Committee. Nagler served as manager of Local 10 from 1939- 1952.
Moe Falikman (1893-1971) came to the United State from Austria-Hungary in 1913 and joined Local 10 of the ILGWU in 1916. Within the ILGWU, he served as comptroller, assistant manager, and eventually, manager of Local 10. He also served as chairman of the American Trade Union Council for Histadrut. Falikman served as manager of Local 10 from 1952-1968.
Biographical / Historical
The Cutters of Local 10 can be traced back to the Gotham Knife Cutters of 1884 and the United Cloak Cutters in 1886 by the Knights of Labor. These were the predecessors of Local 15 and 6 which were chartered by the ILGWU in 1902 and merged to become Local 10 in 1906. Local 10 played a lead role in the 1910 cloakmakers' strike. Local 10 of the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union (ILGWU)was also known as the Amalgamated Ladies' Garment Cutters' Union, and based in New York City. Isidore Nagler was Manager of the Amalgamated Ladies' Garment Cutters' Union, Local 10 of the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union from 1939 to 1952. Moe Falikman succeeded him, serving as manager from 1953 to 1968.
Scope and Contents
The collection is arranged alphabetically by subject and composed predominantly of correspondence. Amalgamated Cutters' Union Local 10 was a member of the Joint Board of Cloak, Suit, Skirt and Reefer Makers' Union, as well as the Joint Board of the Dress and Waistmakers' Union. Local 10 held a unique position in that its members were split between both Joint Boards. Cutters of cloaks belonged to the Cloak Joint Board and cutters of dresses belonged to the Dress Joint Board. Local 10's dual position in the Joint Boards is reflected in the records. Historical information about Local 10 and cutters can be found with the materials documenting the local's 65th anniversary in 1976.
Administrative records include death benefits and disability plans and claims, group contract for the Health and Welfare Fund, names and addresses for members of the executive board as well as business agents, and information on shops that were non-union or "cut-up" shops and employees who became union members.
There is much material of a political nature including promotional material for political campaigns and campaign donations, both for local elections and the 1968 Humphrey presidential campaign. The ILGWU was a supporter of the Liberal Party, and many members of Local 10 were Liberal Party voters illustrated through correspondence about upcoming elections, candidates and fundraising events. There is substantial information on the election of officers for Local 10, including candidates, slates, literature and pamphlets. Of particular importance is the information regarding the installation of officers, as well as correspondence regarding the ILGWU practice (according to Article 5 Section 28 of the ILGWU constitution) that required newly elected and installed officers to sign undated resignation forms to be deposited with the union. The collection contains some of the resignation forms.
There are cases that came before the executive board of Local 10. Cases appear in forms and are identified by individual and their firm, branch and decision. Additionally, there are cases and decisions that were brought before the Impartial Chairman. Some of the personal correspondence involves grievance charges filed and cases against the local. Of particular importance is the information on the Ernest Holmes case, as the collection contains correspondence with the lawyers of the local that handled the case, specifically Emil Schlesinger. Ernest Holmes was a general laborer in a corset factory who filed a complaint with the New York State Commission for Human Rights on April 4, 1961 against Local 10. Holmes alleged discrimination in his employment and request for union membership. One of his claims was that he was denied membership to Local 10. After a year-long investigation, in June 1962, the commission revealed that the evidence offered probable cause in the complaint against the union. The report required that the ILGWU, specifically Local 10, to arrange for employment for Holmes, and assured membership in Local 10 contingent upon satisfactory training and progression of skills. Shortly after filing the initial complaint, Holmes had been dismissed from his job for poor performance. After the ruling and over the course of the next two years, Local 10 worked with Holmes to find suitable employment. Often, his lack of skills in the cutting trade prevented him from keeping some of the jobs. It took Holmes until December 1964 before his membership application was finally granted.
ILGWU General Office folders refer to correspondence with other locals and the International, departments, memos, plant surveys, and the industry. General correspondence to other locals is arranged by local number. Also in the records are member applications for those who registered to participate in the March on Washington. There is correspondence with the Office and Professional Employees International Union Local 153 covered the full time office employees of the union.
Miscellaneous refers to general correspondence with manufacturers and firms, events, meetings or banquets, with other unions, and members. The Manufacturer Associations represented in the collection include: Affiliated Dress Manufacturers, American Cloak and Suit Manufacturers' Association, Associated Corset and Brassiere Manufacturers, Greater Blouse, Skirt and Neckwear Contractors Association, Children's and Juvenile manufacturers (Infants and Children's Coat Association), Industrial Council of Cloak, Suit and Skirt Manufacturers, Merchants Ladies Garment Association, National Skirt and Sportswear Association, New York Coat and Suit Association, and Popular Priced Dress Manufacturers Group.
Finally there are the files of Moe Falikman. Falikman was the manager of Local 10 from 1952-1968, and there is correspondence, but also biographical information and photographs of Falikman.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5780/001: ILGWU. Local 10 minutes 5780/001 mf: ILGWU. Local 10. Microfilm 5780/008: ILGWU. Local 10 dues books 5780/012: ILGWU. Local 10. Managers' correspondence 5780/094: ILGWU. Local 10 membership record books 5780/131: ILGWU. Local 10 records
Women's clothing industry--United States.; Women's clothing industry--New York (State)--New York.; Labor unions--Clothing workers--United States.; Labor unions--Clothing workers--New York (State)--New York.; Clothing workers--United States.; Clothing workers--New York (State)--New York.; Industrial relations--United States.; Industrial relations--New York (State)--New York.; Nagler, Isidore,1895-; Falikman, Moe; Amalgamated Ladies' Garment Cutters' Union.; International Ladies' Garment Worker's Union.
5457237
- A, 1954-1957 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Agreements, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Scope and Contents
  Corres. re agreements, & drafts of agreements w. manufacturers, associations and firms.
- Almanac, 1962-1965 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Cutters' Almanac, 1902-62. Thank you letters for sending publication.
- AFL-CIO, 1957-1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Corres. re AFL State Convention, 1964-68.
- Amun Israeli Housing Corporation, 1956-1967 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Letters requesting redemption of bonds from local members.
- Appellate Division, New York State Supreme Court, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Decision concerning Local 10 members.
- Associated Hospital Service of N.Y., 1967 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Incl. copy of an agreement between Blue Cross & Health & Welfare Fund of the Jt. Bd. of Cloak, Suit, Skirt & Reefer Makers Union & between Blue Cross & Local 10.
- Associations, 1954-1968 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Incl. affiliated Dress Mfrs., Inc., Industrial Council of Cloak, Suit & Skirt Mfrs., Inc.
- Associations, 1954-1967 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Incl. Infants' & Children's Coat Assoc., Inc.
- Associations, 1956-1963 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Incl. Infanta' & Children's Novelties Assoc., Negligee Mfrs. Assoc.
- Associations, 1961-1968 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  New York Coat & Suit Assoc., Inc.
- Associations, 1955-1968 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  New York Raincoat Mfrs. Assoc., Inc.
- B, 1956-1967 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Beth Abraham Home. (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Bruckner, Harry, 1958-1963 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  Corres. re Bruckner case
- Buchwald, Julius, 1960-1966 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Corres. re charges brought by Buchwald against Bernard Zionsky, Business Agent of Local 10, 1965-66, & charges against Assistant Manager Harry Shapiro, 1960-61.
- C, 1956-1969 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Campaign, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  Incl. Union releases and publications on presidential campaign.
- Campaigns, 1952-1965 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  Releases on campaigns.
- Census. (Local 10)., 1961-1966 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Chelsea Cutters, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Class of 1964 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  Corres. on (political) education class of Local 10,
- Cloak, Suit, Skirt and Reefer Makers' Union, Jt. Bd. of, N.Y, 1966-1968 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  Incl. Corres. w. Murray Kolker, Samuel Stuftman, Henoch Mendelsund, 1966-68.
- Cloak Jt. Bd., N.Y., 1962-1965 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Cloak Jt. Bd., N.Y., 1957-1961 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  Incl. proposed amendments to rules and regulations of the Health, Welfare and Severance Fund of the Joint Board; corres. w. Isidore Nagler, 1957-59.
- Cloak Jt. Bd., 1954-1956 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  Corres; report on coat and suit industry by Nagler, March 1954.
- Condolences, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  Letters to Local 10 on death of Moe Falikman; list of contributors to the Moe Falikman Histadrut Scholarship Fund, November 1968.
- Contributions [folder 1 of 2], 1959-1968 (Box 3, Folder 4a)
  Arranged alphabetically by organization.
- Contributions [folder 2 of 2], 1959-1968 (Box 3, Folder 4b)
- Conventions, ILGWU, 1965-1968 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Conventions, ILGWU, 1959-1962 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Cut-up Shop Activities, 1964-1968 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Cutters' resignations as officers of firms, 1957-1958 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- D, 1954-1957 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- D'Armigene, Inc., 1963-1965 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  Case and decision before the National Labor Relations Board.
- Death Benefits, 1954-1968 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  Corres. w. Harry Haskel, Director, Death Benefits Dept. on disabled person membership (sample letters).
- Disability and Health Plans, 1956-1961 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  Memorandums from Morris Sackman, director.
- Dress and Waistmakers' Union, Jt. Bd. of, N.Y., 1957-1965 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Dress Jt. Bd. -Building, 1957-1961 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  Financial and statistical reports.
- Dress Jt. Bd., 1956-1958 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Dress Jt. Bd. Health and Welfare Fund-rules and regulations, procedures. (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Dress Joint Board. Minutes, local managers meetings. [folder 1 of 2], 1956-1959 (Box 4, Folder 7a)
- Dress Joint Board. Minutes, local managers meetings. [folder 2 of 2], 1956-1959 (Box 4, Folder 7b)
- Dressmakers Joint Council, 1958-1968 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  Corres. w. Charles S. Zimmerman, 1958-68; memorandums to local depts. and district managers.
- Dressmakers Joint Council Cut -Up Departments, 1964-1967 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  Audit of firms.
- E, 1955-1962 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Election and Installation of Local 10 Officers [folder 1 of 2], 1968 (Box 5, Folder 2a)
  Incl. pamphlets, circulars, ballot results and related material.
- Election and Installation of Local 10 Officers [folder 2 of 2], 1968 (Box 5, Folder 2b)
- Election and Installation of Officers, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Election and Installation of Officers, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Election and Installation of Officers, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Election and Installation of Officers, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Executive Board Correspondence, 1955-1957 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Executive Board Cases [folder 1 of 2], 1967-1968 (Box 5, Folder 8a)
  Requests from firms to local re employees (sample copies).
- Executive Board Cases [folder 2 of 2], 1967-1968 (Box 5, Folder 8b)
- Executive Board Cases [folder 1 of 2], 1965-1966 (Box 6, Folder 1a)
- Executive Board Cases [folder 2 of 2], 1965-1966 (Box 6, Folder 1b)
- Executive Board Cases, 1963-1964 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Executive Board Cases, 1961-1962 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Executive Board Cases, 1959-1960 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Executive Board Cases, 1954-1958 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Evan-Picone, Inc., (North Bergen, N.Y.), 1966 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  Corres. re negotiations.
- P, 1956-1967 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Financial Reports, 1954 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Q, 1955-1967 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- General Executive Board, ILGWU, 1958-1967 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  Incl. Local 10 reports to G.E.B.; Research Department reports on garment industry.
- Goldenberg, Max, 1954-1957 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- H, 1954-1968 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Handbook for Members, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  Incl. requests for publication.
- Health and Welfare Insurance Plans, 1955-1963 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  Incl. Corres. w. Group Health Insurance, Inc.; Health Insurance Plan (HIP); Associated Hospital Service of N.Y.
- Health and Welfare Fund, 1965-1968 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  Incl minutes of meetings.
- Health and Welfare Fund. Cloak and Dress Joint Board of New York, 1957-1958 (Box 7, Folder 8)
- High School of Fashion Industries, 1954-1968 (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Histadrut (National Committee for Labor Israel - Moe Falikman Chairman), 1968 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  Incl. Corres. on campaigns, speeches of Moe Falikman.
- Histadrut, 1967 (Box 7, Folder 11)
- Hlstadrut, 1965-1966 (Box 7, Folder 12)
- Histadrut, 1963-1964 (Box 7, Folder 13)
- Histadrut, 1961-1962 (Box 7, Folder 14)
- Histadrut, 1954-1960 (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Holmes, Ernest. Case. Complaint brought by Ernest Holmes before the United States Commission for Human Rights charging Local 10 and the Union with discrimination. [folder 1 of 3], 1962-1963 (Box 8, Folder 2a)
  Incl. Corres. w. Emil Schlesinger, legal material.
- Holmes, Ernest. Case. Complaint brought by Ernest Holmes before the United States Commission for Human Rights charging Local 10 and the Union with discrimination. [folder 2 of 3], 1962-1963 (Box 8, Folder 2b)
- Holmes, Ernest. Case. Complaint brought by Ernest Holmes before the United States Commission for Human Rights charging Local 10 and the Union with discrimination. [folder 3 of 3], 1962-1963 (Box 8, Folder 2c)
- I, 1958-1967 (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Impartial Chairman, Cloak Industry, 1957-1968 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  Decisions and reports of Investigations.
- Impartial Chairman, 1957-1965 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  Dress decisions.
- Impartial Chairman, Dress Industry, 1962-1968 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  George Mintzer, Impartial Chairman.
- Industrial Council of Cloak, Suit and Skirt Manufacturers Assoc., Inc., 1954-1961 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  Complaints.
- ILGWU. General Offices, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 2)
- ILGWU. General Offices, 1967 (Box 9, Folder 3)
- ILGWU. General Offices, 1966 (Box 9, Folder 4)
- ILGWU. General Offices, 1965 (Box 9, Folder 5)
- ILGWU. General Offices, 1964 (Box 9, Folder 6)
- ILGWU. General Offices, 1963 (Box 10, Folder 1)
- ILGWU. General Offices, 1962 (Box 10, Folder 2)
- ILGWU. General Offices, 1961 (Box 10, Folder 3)
- ILGWU. General Offices, 1960 (Box 10, Folder 4)
- ILGWU. General Offices, 1959 (Box 10, Folder 5)
- ILGWU. General Offices, 1957-1958 (Box 11, Folder 1)
- ILGWU. General Offices, 1955-1956 (Box 11, Folder 2)
- ILGWU. General Offices, 1954 (Box 11, Folder 3)
- ILGWU Special Assistance Fund, D.D. Administrator, 1966-1968 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  Incl. cases.
- Investigations, 1957-1960 (Box 11, Folder 5)
- Investments (Local 10), 1949-1959 (Box 11, Folder 6)
- Israel, 1961-1968 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  Corres. w. organizations on projects in Israel.
- J, 1955-1968 (Box 12, Folder 1)
- Jewish Chronic Disease Hospital, 1955-1968 (Box 12, Folder 2)
- Jewish Labor Committee, 1955-1967 (Box 12, Folder 3)
- Judiciary Committee Cases and Reports, 1954-1965 (Box 12, Folder 4)
- K, 1956-1966 (Box 12, Folder 5)
- Keyserling, Leon H. Study on the New York Dress Industry, 1963 (Box 12, Folder 6)
- L, 1957-1968 (Box 12, Folder 7)
- Labor Bureau - New York Coat and Suit Industry Report, 1957 (Box 12, Folder 8)
- Labor Day Parades, 1959-1968 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  Corres., releases and printed material.
- Liberal Party, 1965-1968 (Box 13, Folder 1)
- Liberal Party, 1963-1964 (Box 13, Folder 2)
- Liberal Party, 1960-1962 (Box 13, Folder 3)
- Liberal Party, 1954-1959 (Box 13, Folder 4)
- Lieberman, Katz and Aronson, (Attorneys), 1965-1968 (Box 13, Folder 5)
- Lieberman, Katz and Aronson, 1954-1964 (Box 13, Folder 6)
- Lists, Local officers, 1962-1968 (Box 13, Folder 7)
- Local Unions, 9-32, 1942-1968 (Box 14, Folder 1)
- Local Unions, 35-89, 1954-1968 (Box 14, Folder 2)
- Local Unions, 91-600, 1954-1968 (Box 14, Folder 3)
- M, 1954-1967 (Box 14, Folder 4)
- March on Washington, 1963 (Box 14, Folder 5)
- Membership Requests, 1957 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  Employers requesting Union to grant employee membership in Local.
- Miller, Milton, 1960 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  Case.
- Miscellaneous, 1968 (Box 14, Folder 8)
- Miscellaneous, 1967 (Box 14, Folder 9)
- Miscellaneous, 1966 (Box 14, Folder 10)
- Miscellaneous, 1964-1965 (Box 15, Folder 1)
- Miscellaneous, 1961-1963 (Box 15, Folder 2)
- Miscellaneous, 1954-1960 (Box 15, Folder 3)
- N, 1954-1968 (Box 15, Folder 4)
- National Labor Relations Board, 1957-1967 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  Cases
- New York City Central Labor Council, 1962-1968 (Box 15, Folder 6)
- New York State Department of Labor, 1959-1963 (Box 15, Folder 7)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1955-1958 (Box 15, Folder 8)
- Non-Union Shop Lists, 1962-1966 (Box 15, Folder 9)
- O, 1955-1962 (Box 15, Folder 10)
- Office Employees International Union (OEIU), 1965-1967 (Box 15, Folder 11)
  Corres. pertaining to collective bargaining agreements w. Union; Incl. agreements.
- P, 1955-1968 (Box 16, Folder 1)
- Peter Pan Foundations, Inc., 1966 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  Corres. re collective agreement; incl. agreement of 1966.
- Photo Marking Shops, 1958-1960 (Box 16, Folder 3)
- (Conference of) Presidents of Major American Jewish Organizations, 1957-1963 (Box 16, Folder 4)
- Proposals for Agreements, 1963-1964 (Box 16, Folder 5)
- R, 1954-1958 (Box 16, Folder 6)
- Reports. Labor Bureau, New York Coat and Suit Industry, 1955-1959 (Box 16, Folder 7)
- Resolutions, 1960 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  November 1960. Pension increases.
- S, 1954-1968 (Box 16, Folder 9)
- Schlesinger, Emil, Benjamin and Peter, Attorneys for Local, 1966 (Box 16, Folder 10)
  Incl. judgement entered against Princess Ann Girl Coat, Inc. March 1966.
- Seminars, 1959-1960 (Box 16, Folder 11)
- Sixty-Fifth (65) Anniversary of Local, 1967 (Box 16, Folder 12)
  April 22, 1967.
- T, 1955-1966 (Box 17, Folder 1)
- Tax Release Forms, 1959 (Box 17, Folder 2)
- Tour, Israel and Europe, 1960 (Box 17, Folder 3)
- Tributes, 1958 (Box 17, Folder 4)
- U, 1953-1968 (Box 17, Folder 5)
- Unity House, 1954-1968 (Box 17, Folder 6)
- V, 1955-1965 (Box 17, Folder 7)
- W, 1954-1966 (Box 17, Folder 8)
- The Workmen's Circle, 1954-1968 (Box 17, Folder 9)
- X-Y-Z, 1955-1966 (Box 17, Folder 10)
- Falikman, Moe, Personal, 1966-1968 (Box 17, Folder 11)
- Falikman, Moe, 1963-1965 (Box 17, Folder 12)
- Palikman, Moe, 1961-1962 (Box 17, Folder 13)
- Falikman, Moe, 1958-1960 (Box 17, Folder 14)
- Falikman, Moe, 1954-1957 (Box 17, Folder 15)
  Incl. congratulatory messages upon election to vice, president, May 1956.
- Falikman, Moe, Photographs. (Box 17, Folder 16)
  30 photographs.